software engineering radio episode 42
interview with Lego homepage
[Music]
so let's get followed I guess so welcome
to this episode of soft engineering
radio this time we have a guest which is
gregor hopi or how do you pronounce this
for the American audience well actually
that is how you pronounce it I would say
worldwide right okay it's supposedly
okay great so before we actually start
talking about messaging which is the
topic of today's podcast what's your
background what do you do and how do you
get in how did you get into the topic of
enterprise architecture and messaging
yeah I work currently actually at Google
but it's it's somewhat of a interesting
and an unfortunate little bit long story
how I got into the whole integration
patterns and messaging patterns story
which in short it goes a little bit
along the lines that I was working in
consulting and you know that the
consulting companies when they are many
of them when they staff somebody as long
as you heard something along the terms
they think you're like an expert so what
happened was that I used to work with
Vidya and I was staffed on a typical
project and say well this guy knows ya
bitchier then you know working with a
different vendor to ownio should be
trivial and yeah they sold me to the
client for how many hundred dollars an
hour I'm like oh my god yeah what am I
gonna do and the interesting part was
that after I scrambled through all the
vocabulary and the new tool to realize
these things actually do essentially the
same thing
exam you know every vendor has their own
little you know spin their own little
vocabulary etc so slowly the idea form
that okay there must be an easy way to
deal with these messaging process
modeling transformation tools etc and
that it would be a huge benefit for
somebody to have a pattern language or
something that helps bring design
guidance without everytime having to
learn so the vendor specific version
right so that that's what brought you to
writing this book yeah which is called
enterprise integration patterns and it's
basically about messaging right so the
the idea there is and maybe this is a
little bit of hindsight but the plan is
that this would be one of multiple
volumes around enterprise integration
patterns so all the people have asked
why is it not called messaging patterns
why are called enterprise integration
patterns and the main reason is the
thing is already 700
pages in the first place at some point
we just had to stop writing and working
on messaging first yeah is natural it's
sort of a the lowest layer it's sort of
the foundation for a lot of integration
service architectures etc and I'm now
very very slowly working towards a
second volume where we would talk much
more about conversation patterns process
handling it's what's going to ask if we
consider messaging as the foundation of
enterprise integration what's going to
be on top of this foundation what are
the other building blocks of integration
patterns things and he said conversion
is one right yes so conversations are
two years so basically the way I would
look at this is is messaging is sort of
the underlying architectural style I
mean that's what brings a lot of the the
core architectural properties like the
decoupling etc then of course you can
easily easily see that the next
interesting thing is well whatever I
need to send more than one message and
you know it's not always sufficient to
just like send a message and say oh that
was my whole interaction they often you
send a message you get a respond you
confirm you acknowledge you revise and
this is where the whole topic of
conversation starts which is essentially
rather than looking at one message that
travels through a number of different
places which is essentially sort of the
pipes and filters yeah architecture
where you see will really follow a
message which which really highlights in
a sense the the sort of architectural
property of the stateless sort of flow
driven your this message asynchronously
goes through all these steps which is
nice but then in a business application
often as I mentioned you come to a point
where you have a little process or
messages go back and forth between the
same number of parties and this is where
sort of conversations come in
choreography or collaboration we're
gonna start talking about air handling
mechanisms because once I talk more
about state if you think about it
enterprise integration plan has the book
as it is right now is essentially all
stateless as a few pattern we have sort
of like these segue patterns where yeah
we mentioned process manager but it's
sort of really just way and this is a
huge topic and we just sort of put a
link like the umbrella pedal for the
potentially big sub language exactly but
exactly we stuck with Neos
taylor's message flow and then once you
have the vocabulary of state you can
start thinking about you know
compensation schemes
error error management etc etc and so
that would be all the new topics okay so
before we dig into some of the details
of those messaging patterns what's the
characteristics of a message oriented
design why would I want to do messaging
over for example let's say distributed
objects or RPC style applications and in
the days of service on your architecture
that's a pretty pretty common question
actually the the key difference is
really in minimizing the dependencies
between the systems and when people talk
about dependencies they often think
about or while I have a registry or
something where I look up which service
I talk to and that is definitely one
aspect of minimizing dependency but it
goes it goes a lot further
there's dependencies two kinds of
dependencies that that I want to
highlight which is a temporal dependency
and also a dependency of the interaction
style and I think people to really focus
on when they talk about coupling right
we'd like to be loosely coupled the
other these days you can talk anything
about SOA or distributed systems without
talking about coupling so when you talk
about coupling what makes coupling are
dependencies between systems and as I
said yeah there's a quite broad range so
like location dependency and I can solve
that with a registry technology
dependency I can use XML or whatever to
fix that but what really gets
interesting is of the the temporal
dependencies and the interaction style
that's why I think messaging really
shines because it's asynchronous which
means that the sender doesn't
necessarily or the interaction style
doesn't sort of it you know inherently
require the sender to wait for the whole
interaction to be completed the sender
sends the message of it goes on the
queue as far as the sender is is
concerned this is reliable queuing etc
as far as the sender is concerned the
sender is done this thing is on its way
and and you can always say well you know
I can make an RPC call and I just have
another thread or something or or people
sort of you have a middleman object yeah
or like a little sort of delegates and
sort of like an event-based the
for example you can make sort of HDPE
synchronous web service calls with
various stacks like for example Internet
and just sort of get a callback get a
delegate callback when it's actually
done but the problem is that's sort of
like an illusion you create at the
application layer if it's not actually
an architectural style so that messaging
the style itself sort of has the notion
of that the sender is not locked up with
the timing of the receiver and that's
what I call you get temporal decoupling
and it's so inherently in the way you
design the system it's not like a little
API trick you sort of play on yourself
although it's funny because many people
say that if you use XML as the message
format your technology independent and
everybody can use it but of course you
have to agree on the semantic content on
the DTD on the meaning and the schema
it's somewhat the same with this
temporal decoupling what you say is of
course obviously yeah every would agree
of course so but you had you don't have
a technical temporal coupling but
depending on the business process you
might still rely on the fact that the
other side sends a reply message within
a certain time box right so there might
be that that the system doesn't work if
the other one isn't up and running
because it can't do a sensible job
although it's technically decoupled so
again this is the difference between
technical stuff right and an application
process stuff so right yeah and and that
is of course true I mean so a magic you
know rarely happens also in some sense
that if the other service is an
available messaging isn't nice so
suddenly gonna make it available but it
think makes you think about the
interaction between them very
differently in Melvin yeah maybe you
write the calling application that it
can actually do as much it could
possibly do without having the response
message or you even already assume that
the request and response go back to the
same place it could move on yeah to
another system that could be a longer
change that is that's probably the most
important aspect here that if you use a
messaging oriented style of application
development you think differently and
therefore you design your applications
in a way that if the other guy is not
available you don't simply do nothing
but
you wait you know it's easier to wait on
a reply message and do a timeout then on
our pcs because it's not a technical
exception stuff so it helps you design
systems that actually cope with the
other participant not being available
yeah and I always tried very true I what
I do I try to remind people also that in
the real world
everything is message based in
asynchronous it's like if I want to call
you and you're not home I am NOT gonna
sit on the phone for four hours waiting
till you get back and pick up the phone
right yeah that would be like that the
dumbest possible way but then sometimes
I think in the world of computer science
we've become so used to the cost at
command and control infrastructure or
paradigm if you wish yeah because it's
so very comfortable for us to work in
it's addictive all and we know exactly
what's gonna happen but the real world
doesn't work like that and you know
service aren't architectures and
distributed systems are a lot more like
the real world they're struggled with
some of the same real world problem like
you're not home yeah and so I need to
really think about differently now of
course if I need to ask you a burning
question yeah just using messaging can't
magically make that happen right but I
can a reduce my effort enormous Lee
because I'm not you know sitting on the
phone till waving back and yeah I don't
have to poll like all the every 30
minutes I'll leave you a voicemail
message essentially and I think as you
there you can call me back so overall
it's the most efficient interaction yeah
and I think you hit the very good point
these architectural styles they're very
much about changing your mind yeah it's
the the technology Goni goes so far but
then once you change your sort of
mindset the way you look at the
application suddenly you get a lot more
ideas and say well you know I'm building
a website how could this possibly
asynchronous because it's all HTTP on
the front end but then once you sort of
have this mindset a lot good lot of good
ideas come like for example Amazon they
do a very short portion of their process
synchronously yeah basically Allah says
thank you for your order yeah it's like
so just make sure the data is logged
somewhere and then everything else is
asynchronous oh you bad credit card out
of stock shipment delayed your stuff in
ship thank you
senator some feedback it's it's all
asynchronous or people start having
sort of Ajax II type clients where you
know they make requests and data comes
in in the background so I mean Ajax I
guess it's a perfect example that's
being on a web page does not necessarily
mean you're completely synchronous and
and so I think once you sort of think
more you change your pattern of thought
and this is really what these
architectural styles are about you very
quickly come up you know like three
different systems right the things that
that you thought were sort of your you
know constraints that he couldn't
overcome well it has to be synchronous
suddenly it doesn't seem like such a
hard problem anymore and and that's sort
of the softer side of messaging but I
think it's very very important yeah and
and and if we talk about messaging then
we primarily talk about like enterprise
system service-oriented systems because
it is interesting to see that message
oriented style of developing
applications isn't restricted to that
domain rather the embedded folks
real-time folks use message passing
quite a lot I mean many embedded systems
even be the MPI write this message
passing interface for high-performance
parallel computing is based on messages
so rather ubiquitous concept but we're
talking about the stuff in the context
of like enterprise integration
service-oriented architecture okay so I
think this is the target discussion
mm-hmm
so before we look at some of the more
detailed patterns what's the
relationship to service-oriented
architecture at Yahoo where we actually
record this interview we're in I'm not
supposed to say we're in my hotel room
right okay edit this out maybe so you
hosted a track on service-oriented
architecture so what's the what's the
relationship between messaging and SOA
is message SOA just messaging with with
you know the message message through
messages describe using WSDL or how do
you see the relationship mm-hmm there so
the track was called SOA what's left to
say and besides just rhyming yeah if we
sort of the theme or even notice that it
rhymes because I always face so ah ah
yeah there's a whole other debate yeah I
was just told by Patrick there be a just
send an official memo that it has to be
called SOA
so at least a B ei because I guess it's
B
yeah they didn't want people to call it
beer and so on maybe so now we're moving
closer it's SOA what's left to say but
the spirit of the track was very much
yeah so what's what's really in this SOA
thing and I think so now your question
already actually
so the presuppose is a very important
relationship that actually wasn't as
clear in the very beginning that you
already assumed that SOA implies
messaging oh I don't I just tried to ask
the question provocatively I don't I
think you should because in the
beginning people you know saw SOA very
much equals web services and luckily
we're overcoming that when we say SOA is
an architectural stuff and and so from
that perspective it's it's no longer
tied to just sort of HTTP you know soap
soap messages but what people quickly I
think started to realize that a sort of
RPC based model for a service or an
architecture is actually not the optimal
the optimal style because for the
reasons we just discussed exactly I mean
we start talking about loose coupling
and temporal the company etc our service
owner architecture is it's about a loose
coupling and B it's also about a
simplified interaction model and that's
where messaging is a very important
ingredient in a sense that if you think
about in the very beginning I touched on
this briefly where we say that coupling
is the notion about how much the systems
depend on each other so how many
assumptions they are a RPC style
interaction actually makes quite a few
sort of requirements to us it seems
trivial because everybody knows when a
method call is yeah but actually there's
quite a bit going on this this whole
notion that oh I have one request and I
have one response and they belong to
each other in the collar weights and the
collar essentially continues after the
response comes back so that's quite a
bit baked in there which you know in a
services would we don't want to be so
restrictive and says well this is just
one way of doing it and there might be
others right it's one way in many cases
it's not not the most most suitable way
and that's where all the conversation
patterns come into play because maybe I
want to send one messaging at a stream
of mess
just maybe I have a more complex
interaction where there might be a
message later to compensate for
something and I think that's where the
notion that really these are
conversations made out of messages a
give you much better catalogue of
interactions and also they they get you
out of this sort of RPC thinking if you
have if you starting to think oh it's
one message at a time and then they
correlated we start talking about
choreography etc and it becomes a much
more interesting topic because service
ordered architecture to a large extent
is not about what's inside these
applications of these services it's very
much about the interaction and when you
really want to focus on the interaction
aspect thinking about it as messages
makes a lot more sense so if I want to
be provocative I'd say you'd buy the
typical busting or some other messaging
middleware you send around XML messages
for interoperability and you have some
way of dealing with these different
interactions actually interaction
patterns then you're actually then you
have so of course there are all these
organizational aspects and business
driven and stuff but technically this
would constitute a service or extra
architecture probably the contract and
registry aspects okay so I would still
think I would want to have somewhere so
I have some form of discovery and to
some extent using message channels can
sort of supplement consignment for them
because if the right thing happens to
listen on the right channel that's
essentially like registering yourself
for something contracts I think are
important ingredient like knowing and
understanding what a service can do so
what does the contract describe it
describes probably the data structures
that go in and out of a service so it
describes the structure of a message and
it also describes the interaction
patterns that like using for example
state machine protocol state machine
that describes what goes in what comes
out under which conditions yes I believe
so but they are they are a handful of
challenges the one is sort of a
philosophical challenge and that is how
much should you actually put in your
contract and this is the whole like rest
versus soap debate but I would say once
you believe in contracts then the
contract should actually do a little bit
more than just the syntax of the message
solutely it should to grab the style
unfortunately whistle isn't very good at
that you have this good at nothing
actually to be honest I think anyway my
opinion yeah well I would say like that
the most useful part of whistle is the
schema which isn't really there's a lot
to be said about the challenges of
schemas in the first place but it's not
very good to actually describe the
interaction so whistle - oh is actually
gonna have a pluggable message exchange
pattern whatever you want to call a busy
you can sort of specify your own message
exchange patterns through URIs and there
was because of the realization that you
know the interaction starts the
conversations would be would be more
interesting it doesn't have a spec for
how you describe the conversations
essentially you just make a URI and say
this means a certain type of
conversation it doesn't have a rule
language or state machine actually I
think this is a joke right I mean the
embedded talks have been using state
machines to describe protocols which are
interactions for a long time
yeah in the choreography guys you
probably saw are now singing singing the
sort of the misery of the the
choreography people who are the closest
to using a state machine to modeling the
conversational state yeah so when you
look at the conversation meaning sort of
like a protocol for like which messages
go which way under under which rules
there is a huge battle between the
conversation over the course or the
choreography and the orchestration guy
says too many words were see in the
whole service or a same thing or no very
very difficult in heated debate so yeah
you don't know it gets very entertaining
at every sort of web service event there
is lunacy put a choreography person and
an orchestration person together and you
know serve a few beers
it gets generally very interesting the
fundamental difference being and the
funny thing is that they are sort of
it's like a dualistic view of the world
so you can discuss forever and
essentially the choreography people look
at the conversation state they say we
don't care about the endpoints so much
we really just want to observe what
messages go back and forth
a middleman who watches both exactly he
doesn't have to be a middleman that he's
plugged-in but observer yeah it's the
observer and say here's the rules about
what messages go and I could have more
than two endpoints for example yes or no
watch that goes on and I have rules
about what goes on versus the
orchestration folks very much come from
the respective of a service endpoint a
service provider and they say here's an
abstract process that has send and
receive actions in it so that's a
particle state machine classically yeah
there's a protocol state machine from
the viewpoint of one endpoint of a
single endpoint and you can see that
they're very so dualistic I mean the
most simple sort of a quest response
again is the process would look like I
have a beginning action in my process
begins I receive a message I perform the
computation and I send a correlated
response message and so you have like
three actions in this BPL process maybe
whatever you use to make that
orchestration yeah and in case of BPL
for example the business process
execution language this is actually also
described through a whistle docume and
one of their processes is always
described externally through a whistle
document it manifests itself as such so
it's very clear if a service yeah in the
coreography world there would be one
conversation on state essentially with a
single conversational state as I'm
waiting for the response and you could
sort of describe essentially expect one
message to go and now I'm in this more
state wait for response and then once a
message comes back the conversation ends
so it's very similar but it's sort of
different viewpoints and especially once
you start talking about having more than
two participants getting out of this
consumer provider model then the the
choreography you know it's a nicer way
to describe it where it gets interesting
is that so intellectually I like the
notion of the choreography the problem
is the standards are nearly in far
enough along they've been many failed
attempts as sort of doing more in this
world it's like the whiskey the the
webservice choreography interface there
are many stone and failed attempts
because I think that just best
signifying the conversation it's a
relatively abstract parts you want to go
and build in
so having like an orchestration where
you have a little process and there's
tool and people is pretty far along it's
a spec as well you just put this
together and you have it and it runs
verses so intellectually the
choreography is appealing but it's
always had a very hard time getting
mainstream adoption and then the support
and that's so that's exactly that's
where those those battles those battles
happen okay so now we talked a lot about
the book you didn't write yet which is
interactions and conversations and
choreography and these things of course
that's more interesting right and you
should actually you know tour the world
and promote it you're so fed up with the
content that you don't want to see it
anymore but still I'm sorry but let's go
back to messaging a little bit so so can
you
I mean your book is a pattern language
right so it contains how many lines 65
60 Oh quite a bit so can you can you I
mean we were not going to recite the
whole pattern language now but I think
we should do two or three things one is
you should you probably have chapters or
something so areas of interest which are
covered by several patterns so maybe
just cover these different areas and
then we should may maybe pick up four or
five of the most important patterns and
like this top most area or something so
what are the main areas of concern in
messaging systems for which your panel
language language contains patterns and
it's good to actually go back to
messaging and the way you phrased it I I
quite like it because it sort of
highlights the fact that messaging is
the foundation right for all this other
stuff we can talk about the other stuff
a long time but it all comes back down
to fundamentally message based face
interaction so what we did is in the
pattern spoke and your parents has
become so like a word where if you want
to boost your book say autistic like the
pattern word and the title and you think
that's true I think we just may be
overcome it but I would say in the last
two years it was very popular to have
pattern and I think people started to
realize that you know the parents are
not all what they cooked up there so I
think they maybe slowly coming back to
parents mean real parents but I think I
like your question because the lang
which aspect it's one of the key
properties that people tend to
underestimate a pattern isn't just like
a pattern there's a very important
reason patterns have names and they have
names you can make sentences out of them
yeah and when you make sentences out of
it you know they form a language and
they're supposed to have sort of
somewhat of a common structure so you
can make meaningful sentences so so we
did that and we thought very carefully
about how we structure our language and
if you think about back to gang of four
and you know there's some structure
you know there's creational patterns and
they're structural patterns there's
behavioral patterns so they're they're
not a language right because they don't
build the whole so those Goff is like a
collection of patterns that are packaged
into different concerns or aspects
creational behavior but there are not a
language in the sense that if you apply
them in some sequence or in some way
they build a consistent hole yours is
different it's a language in the sense
that if you apply those patterns you
create this whole big messaging
infrastructure right yeah maybe you
should have a session with Ralph Johnson
where you tell him his book is now the
pattern language same igoing interesting
what I think community agrees maybe
Ralph doesn't but the community probably
agrees that it's it's a collection of
parents or a system of parents or that's
not a language in the sense that it
builds this whole right so so I think
what is unique parent theorem it may be
not not unique but what is interesting
in our book is that we structured it
along a set of root patterns right and
then we drill down from each root
patterns the root patterns basically
give you the key pieces that you
essentially need to build one of those
solutions that's where you're right I
think the the the structure is quite
different and in the back inside cover
of the book we were able to basically
show a set up for the typical messaging
system where you have a sender a message
it goes on a channel there's some
transformation there's an endpoint that
receives it and then there's sort of a
little bit of system management
monitoring on it and it so it turns out
those are actually like the root
patterns like the prototypical picture
of what this thing all the pieces you
need it's a little bit like a shopping
list and say more likely than not I will
need those six things okay so a became
they became the the root
so basically what they are is we have
channel patterns because I need to have
a messaging channel we have message
patterns because I need to put a mass
message on there then we have a routing
patterns because I need to get the
message to we're actually supposed to go
we have transformation because you know
most likely more likely than not the two
endpoints have have different data
formats then we have endpoint patterns
because actually the message has to be
consumed that this is sort of the whole
event-driven
asynchronous message thing so I hits the
synchronous object-oriented application
so it's an interesting topic as well and
then we have systems management and
monitoring which is something that seems
more peripheral and say well I don't
need that really you know that doesn't
really make the messages go but it's
something that's very close to my heart
because these very dynamic loosely
coupled asynchronous solutions you don't
have like them if you don't have decent
monitoring and management you very
quickly get yourself into trouble
because essentially what you do with
these loosely coupled dynamic solutions
you defer a lot of the decisions to run
time a lot of things that in traditional
designs you would sort a hard code or
baked into basically at coding and
compile time yeah now I'm very dynamic
and flexible at runtime you can reassign
channel names reroute stuff put on more
no it's in whatever you can do
so when you make that decision you get a
lot of architectural properties you can
scale and lose couple and whatnot you
have but it also means that you need
sort of equivalent to us because you
don't get syntax errors anymore if you
mess up the day.i or you know if your
messages don't go in the right place you
don't get a stack trace right it's like
you have to have a whole new set of
tools and that's why we made system
systems management and monitoring a
first-class pattern in the book as well
and then each of those things have a
root pattern so there's a message
channel there's the message there's the
message router message transformation
there's the endpoint and then there's
also systems management and then each of
those basically you know blows up into a
whole chapter where I say okay I know I
need a router and then I sort of go to
the chapter of routing and then I have
sort of 11 or 12 message routing
patterns and I have so little catalog
a little we put even together so have a
little decision matrix yeah where you
can sort of help decide which one you
want to choose
so then typically these sub patterns
under each of these root patterns are
alternatives that should be applied in
different contexts or or maybe let's
briefly I mean let's briefly go through
each of these categories
root patterns and briefly discuss what
kind of alternatives there are in each
of them so if you say there is this root
pattern channel what kind of variability
is there or what's the different
alternatives with regards to channels
maybe I thought maybe there's some
persistence general there's
transactional channels there's probably
channels that are secure or what's the
kind of variability here mm-hmm yeah and
I think generally what you described
that there's a root pattern and from
there going to no alternatives is it's
generally correct the one thing I do
want to highlight is that patterns are
not sort of painting by numbers yeah
it's not we're sort of just go down some
checklist and magically I arrive at the
one single answer yeah the very reason
we use patterns is because that's how
software architecture does not actually
work so so you have this list of
ingredients and they have a certain
sweet spot but you can always combine or
you can always find something new so
it's not like you go down this check
list you find a perfect one yeah however
what it can do it can help you sort of
choose what are things you need to
consider so you mentioned channel
patterns so the things that are
interesting about a channel are a the
semantics of the message propagation and
consumption and this is where choose in
this case it's a relatively immediate
choice between two options is point a
point or publish/subscribe right alright
so you know if I have multiple
subscribers do they compete for one
message and it's guaranteed the message
goes only one plays or is this I send a
message and any number of subscribers
will get it and this is just you sort of
have a mini sidebar here this is where
the parents really help in a sense that
yeah you see that these are two fairly
different choices but the parents can
really explain a lot of the subtleties
and the nuances so for example a publish
subscribe channel has a very interesting
property which is adding new consume
a side-effect free but it doesn't impact
the consumers that are already there
versus at a point of point channel
adding another consumer takes messages
from the phone so you better it's it's
good for scaling because you have
moderate consumers that off the same
type but if you bond something sort of
more event oriented and can't just like
add a second one yet you would actually
have to put a T on which is one of our
other routing pattern right yeah it was
exactly where you're like one channel
goes in and the same thing goes on two
output channels you manually build it
but so it goes into a lot of those
nuances but back to your original
question so it's you know it's sort of
the semantics of the message propagation
in the subscription then it's inherent
properties of the channel so it's a
durability for example is it's an
important one yes this persistent or non
persistent and then we also have
channels that for a special uses so for
example you would have an invalid
message channel so for example if we're
a if a so receiver receives a message
that it can actually not process rather
than just tossing that message because
then we would never know that this
actually happened or around the log and
in some log file well we're gonna
distribute a message or in system why
not use messaging to represent that and
route that that message on a specific
channel that's designated as a channel
for messages that could not be processed
yeah so this gives you a good choice
about and you can combine some of those
like for example I could have a durable
point-to-point invalid message channel
right if I want to it so let's take a
brief look at some of the alternatives
with regards to adding message what's
the next one so what are the points
there yes
and of course it's again one of those
topics that sounds a bit more trivial
than really is I have to put a message
on this that's why some of our original
patterns are more just to form the
vocabulary right yeah the message route
pattern itself is not some like you know
incredible insight that we had as like
yes you know a message goes on there but
what we try to highlight is what what
actually makes a good message our
messages are not objects and they are
there that often the document trees but
that
even have to be like in a typical world
a lot of it was your name equals value
so different structure no pointers you
know different type system off and etc
so there's a lot of subtleties and and
even I wish that we would have a bit
more about what actually makes a good
message design and I'm still looking for
the book that says hey here's a good
message and here's a bad message and
here's why
we quite honestly didn't even get to
that point either what we did we focus
primarily on sort of what is the message
used as the nice thing is about that the
patterns don't always just have to
describe a technical solution yeah
patterns can also focus very much so on
the intent yeah so we have a event
message a document message and command
message right it's a message exactly is
a message that you know is intended to
like instruct the other end to do
something and the conversation could
still be more than just playing our PC
but the ideas it's like I'm sending a
command versus I'm sending a document
like here's an order or something versus
I'm sending an event which is like an
order was placed but not necessarily do
I have the order in err message yeah so
so that gives you again some choices and
then on top of that it gives you
important what's often considered header
fields like another term is often used
like out-of-band metadata yeah
out-of-band metadata basically it's all
the stuff that is very useful a
messaging system which is not the actual
payload so that's where we talk a
correlation identifiers right we're
living in the land of icing right
synchrony now so if I send three
messages and three come back it would be
very bad assumption to assume that the
three that come back and the same order
as the three I sensor I need to
correlate correlation identifier is also
known as asynchronous completion token
and the crime or technical world right
it is it is very very similar an idea I
would say the the completion token has a
bit more of the application view so to
kick off a process and I all right so
this token destroy the state the message
identify is essentially the same larger
pattern but sort of it focuses more
while here's the thing I stick into the
message which is sort of indicative that
we focus more on the interaction than
the application but of course the forces
and the thought process and why realism
is essentially identical and a lot of
applications when they use a correlation
at any fire
they actually use it to keep the state
etc so when it comes back they use it
exactly like an AC te right up Thank You
state however now world we go more
quickly to sort of like the
conversational aspect but we look at all
this identifies in this message now can
we pass this identifying through a whole
conversation that goes through Ryan stop
and that's what the okay different
slightly different yeah
same fundamental forces so we have
things like return address and
correlation identifier etc so that gives
you a good idea of what should be in a
message header and it turns out that
most commercial messaging system see any
JMS implementation or any typical video
web methods kind of thing the WS
addressing etc they all have these kind
of patterns already built in because
once you have some form of asynchronous
interaction you really need to have some
of those core patterns but it makes
sense to have a common name it makes
sense to describe why they are so
important and also it's important to say
well what if I don't use those fields
what assumptions do i bake into my
design so if I say doing something very
simple I don't need a correlation
identifier because me I just like send
one message or something which is what
we find it good but then the pattern
reminds you is like what here's the
assumptions you just made something you
just made is that you have order
guarantee channels and then you probably
only have a single consumer yeah because
as soon as you have more than one
processing unit they run in parallel you
build a distributed parallel system
order is the first thing that's what
goes out the window
so essentially you precluded yourself
from scaling out and so the pattern is
very nice even though the pattern itself
isn't like rocket science it's like oh
yeah a correlation identifier you know
most people can figure out what that is
but once you sort of highlight people or
here's the assumption you just baked in
by not using their field so it's nice to
remind you of the ramifications
absolutely I'm not using something you
can use the patterns in Reverse yeah
that's why patterns that have somewhat
like an obvious idea in them are still
like seven pages long because they
discuss all those trade-offs and I think
it's that's why parents are useful
they're relevant even though the
solution itself is known and often built
into the
platform right the discussion and
reminding people is enormous ly valuable
and we have no problem filling 700 some
pages with what we believe is
interesting stuff on the field that I
would love to be much better understood
but quite honestly a field verse lot of
vendor implementations already I mean
it's not like research him and it's like
you know that stuff is out that exists
but there was a lot that was left to say
now exactly for that reason that's why
we chose patterns at the format
absolutely okay let's look at the
routing patterns and what it's they're
specific that you mentioned the t thing
before like one channel you know
separates into two channels and the nice
thing the nice thing about messaging is
that you can find a lot of real world
analogy so you know the T is essentially
like so your little double yeah so you
know your socket multiply right we can
put two power plugs you know into one or
you you split your video signal and two
so you can watch in a bedroom in the
living room kind of thing so some of the
rounding pendants are very much like
that you know it's almost like schematic
type stuff yeah message goes in one
channel it goes out on - but routers can
be pretty complex so there's a lot of
what we do is around again the semantics
so is this router gonna send a single
message out yeah
is the router gonna send multiple
messages if you have this t thing does
it decide for each message where it goes
or will it like like like the electrons
right photons actually go through both
of those yes channels the T is like the
stupid photon it just goes both sides
yeah and so it's good it's like a
splicer right you sort of like we call a
wiretap as well actually so because you
put it in the main stream and your
parcel of message is a pattern yeah but
it's like the little splicer fly so why
tell other patterns are much more
intelligent about where things go on the
key pattern there's the content-based
router so it's something that looks at
the content off the message itself and
based on that decides where the message
goes now there's still a distinction
that we have between a content-based
router which sends the message to a
single place versus a recipient list
which sent the message to multiple
places and you start seeing there's sort
of a nice spectrum he's saying oh well
where's the difference between a recipie
list and a publish/subscribe channel
right because doesn't publish subscribe
channel already do that yeah it does
ends the messages and that's again where
the patterns are just a very good format
to discuss the nuances in a published
subscribe channel a you generally have a
common Slough okay you know element big
word use you know open bracket ontology
closing bracket big values and you have
some sort of common ontology or
structure that defines where all
receivers have to express what they
interested in it's usually a topic space
or the name of a channel it's like oh
I'm interested in channel a B C or D F
or I'm subscribing to this topic which
is called y'all like order dot new
something rather sort of some sort of
hierarchy but you have to have a common
agreement on this language is of who
subscribes to what and the subscription
is very much at the control of the
consumer mm-hm
the recipient list is an active routing
element that sits in the middle so it
incorporates its own language the
consumers can't really say much about it
but it has many more degrees of freedom
and freedom of what it wants to route by
so it could say you know the textbook
example so if the order comes in for
less than a thousand dollars it goes
here and if it's more than a thousand
dollar course here but it could also
decide to send it both places or some
certain escalation schemes or the the
topic that we have the example we have
in our book is you're making a request
for a loan and there's three banks you
know there's like sort of the premium
bank there's the all-around bank and
then there's the loan shark and it turns
out that each bank only likes to service
certain customers so I router sense it
to marginal banks because you want to
get the best quote but the banks require
us to kind of pre-filter a little bit
because the bank doesn't to deal you
know the premium bank doesn't want to
deal with the decrepit customers so we
did that as an example and it turned out
that the loan shark was actually the
bottleneck in the system and the reason
the loan shark became the bottleneck
because the loan shark takes everybody
yeah but really does it give you the
best rate yeah right so we optimized our
recipient list just
I go to the launch truck only if you
don't have another destination right and
so immediately these business rules in
their optimize and the system throughput
we I went to a multiple we used some
random data there's just feed it but
when I'm multiple because the launch RQ
was just always backed up and so you can
make very intelligent rounding decisions
and there would be something that a pub
sub channel cannot do right because it's
completely side-effect free you cannot
say oh because this message also goes to
premium which I know they're gonna give
us a good rate I don't even have to
bother to go to a loan shark right so
it's a very important subtle difference
and that's like a dozen of these sort of
different different routing routing
patterns you know look at the website
which will the URL of which will put
into the show notes of course yeah eai
patterns calm okay search for into
google for integration patterns and
you'll be goods yeah you probably hacked
the Google search algorithm since you're
working at Google right so what are some
of the endpoint patterns I actually I
don't really couldn't can't imagine what
these would be actually like the API
towards the the application I know if
you're is you know is a little bit of a
bad word in the patterns community right
would like to distance ourselves from
the people who talk about you guys okay
I'm just so lucky a little
tongue-in-cheek here yeah but now what
would we find the interesting part of
the endpoint is that this is where the
document-oriented asynchronous stuff
hits the object all right at the
synchronous stuff so you have to map it
and that's what I meant by IP I yes so
it's a focus on how you actually get the
message right so there you have the
choice between a polling consumer and
then consumer it's basically how far
into you app can you continue the the
event-driven
nature of this and yeah short answer is
the further the better mostly but no
pattern is a very own Universal so they
are fine reasons where you like to poll
and then it has other things like a
transactional consumer you know
transactions and messaging are a big big
topic of controversy on occasion so it's
to say it's not enough if there is a
transactional channel you actually need
a transactional endpoints we have some
means of controlling the transaction
like beginning and end
the transactions that were you talking
about correct so the the most important
thing is when we talk about transaction
and messaging is that in loosely coupled
system essentially don't want your
transactions to span multiple systems
because yeah the transactions could be
shortly isn't that the whole point of a
transaction yeah in a sense yes or no
but I would say the point of a
transaction is pickiest scope okay okay
it is the point of a transaction within
the scope that you chose so in a
messaging system you choose your scope
of doing a business action and sending a
message as result right and then it's
the role of the messaging system to make
sure that message doesn't actually get
lost I mean it's just like so a database
transaction the role of the database
transaction is do some business
functionality and get data into the
database and you know then make sure it
commits or read something from the
database change according to your
business logic and then update the
database maybe multiple tables and then
make sure that's consistently committed
so in a messaging world we keep the same
local context between the application
the message so very very common
transaction scope is receiving a message
performing a function in sending a
message mmm because that's how you
ensure that between if you have
guaranteed channels if in your
application and this is what a
transaction consumer does it will open a
transaction read the message from the
inbound channel do its work and then
send the message on the outbound channel
in the same transaction because here we
don't have any issues it's a local
application scope yeah and then commit
or rollback so it's not about that the
endpoint controls the transactionality
of the channel it's rather that the it's
like an X I resource right so that the
the client can be a part of the
transaction and do its work in a
controlled bounded fashion correct so
the transaction is the client so when
you say exhale oh I want to be careful
let's say if I have a published
subscribed channel with you know ten
possible consumers the transaction does
not span the 10 consumers right a
transaction deals with each consumers
and the reading of its message and
possibly the sending of another message
so an annotation context is very
application folk not across different
channels or consumers because that would
be some of the emphasis of
coupling of loose coupling and message
event Rio etc you lock everything down
again if you needed to coordinate those
10 folks then you'd have to do this on
an application level so you'd wait until
all of them send the positive reply the
Act message and then you'd on the
application level say okay business
transaction finish or something right
and of course in a business transaction
I mean there's sort of the the
prototypical example of the bank account
one you sent a message to this account
and this account probably don't really
do that but that's sort of the example
that always comes up is like how do I
ensure integrity and this is where you
hit the world off you know different air
handling strategies compensation
etcetera so you usually try to find
alternatives because transaction sends
are loosely coupled messaging just don't
mix at the same level as we describe
they mix in a sense where you have the
transactions around the channel endpoint
and the application but the overarching
messaging architecture doesn't like
transactions of a large of a large scope
because it just goes immediately against
the temporal decoupling the synchrony
etc so did we cover all of the
root-patterns I'm under the impression
that one is missing but I can't remember
mayshen I'm not sure so this test is two
that we haven't covered the
transformation patterns and you know so
the the route pattern I mentioned
beginning one of the nice things we I
think I believe we did is sort of having
these root-patterns language through
pattern is a message transformer and
again it's not a huge surprise that some
air I want the message on the other end
to look like then you know differently
from what you put in and then we have a
couple of subtypes like one is an
enricher and again we talked about a
little bit that the patterns don't
necessarily mean a different technical
solution but I express the intent so a
message transformer is something where I
am it's very generic it's just somehow
it gets transformed the enricher much
more expresses the intent that the
original message was missing something
that the other end wants so I sent a
message in it goes to an external
resource of sorts and then it sticks
additional information into the outbound
message the external resource could be
like a real database or application
where I retrieve information or it could
be like a system resource like a
timestamp you know maybe a message is
missing a time and arrow I can just do
that but the idea is the message gets
sort of bigger on the
and often you know your message
transformer might be doing a little bit
of both but that's where the parents
allow me to express what I think is the
more important property is this more
important that you know I'm augmenting
it or do I just say marriage is like a
general transformation it's just
whatever and then we have the same thing
where you can sort of select pieces
let's say have a very large message but
actually down don't-don't-don't want to
transport all that so I reduce my
message in that sort of you know the
reverse of the enricher and you can
express that the main intent of this of
this transformation was to actually
select a a sort of subset of information
and you know we have a few other
patterns we have something called claim
check where you like store the message
data and basically just pass a key on
okay and then you pick it up later so
that's like it but half a dozen of those
so one one aspect of you lose coupling
is probably also that although you know
you have this temporal decoupling and
and the API and stuff you don't want to
induce a high degree of coupling as a
consequence of having to agree on the
same data structures so you one of the
so so one of these transformers is
probably useful to like the adapter
pattern in golf right so you send one
formative message to this thing and it
converts it to some other schema for
example that is the content is basically
like the same but it's formally
differently expressed so I think this is
a very important aspect of transformers
to decouple that the otherwise appearing
binding between endpoints because of
their agreed upon data structure yes and
it's very very important to realize that
these kind of dependencies and these
kind of bindings can happen at many
different levels and one level is the
data format right and so they're strong
assumptions baked in and there's a
couple things I can do again the
patterns can offer any magic but the
parents can give me good catalog of what
at least my reasonable choices are right
right so in case of different
transformers the main thing is I do I
don't make the problem go away but I
moved a problem in a specific entity of
my choice in fact which is outside of
the systems I know where I'm dealing
with this problem of data format and
also quite honestly often I use a
language that's more suitable to data
transformation now some people argue
technically everywhere the XSLT anything
oh yeah you know there's a lot of
debates but essentially it is you know
for better words it's a language that
only deals for transformation so by
pulling this out into a separate entity
I have more choices in terms of
implementation for example and I very
specifically sort of incarnated the
problem in one place rather than having
lingering in the two end points
operational concerns well it's always a
good good idea yeah yeah so I mean is is
that no magic but good set of choices
and at least you know I have my concern
my problem represented in one spot and
you're exactly right the the message
transformers do that but they go in a
sense they go beyond that as well
because let's say the question is always
should have put all my data on the
channel let the other side pick which
sort protects the sender but it's rather
inefficient or should I only send the
information that I know the receiver
really wants which is a stronger form of
coupling but a lot more efficient right
and that's where I was saying we getting
this whole idea of mieux so the message
selector or the enricher etc and we can
play very much and this is where the
intent of the patterns is important when
I say oh this is really sort of
something that shrinks the message
because I make a bit more assumptions I
have knowledge now but what the other
end needs but I actively put this
element in because I gotta get rid of
these huge mess areas and so I used that
pattern and that icon very specifically
to represent that intent as opposed to
well near the field what's called last
name but it really should be called name
which is like a generic transformer and
that's where the patterns and especially
made little icons for all these patterns
actually quite suddenly become much more
expressive if you look at a system
architecture diagram it shows all XSLT
transform here but the talent see very
very little about why that transformer
right and what the intent is a little
talked about the technology instead of
the concepts which is always a bad idea
Greg member the iconic and now even
though we only have like half a dozen of
these for transformations some of the
core intends I can very quickly Express
and they have these cute little pictures
where your little message becomes a big
message or a big message because a
little message or sort of the
transformation nobody can tell did
somebody come up with a tool where you
can draw these like schematics using
your icons to are to build your
messaging infrastructure interactively
you can draw it so somebody made a Visio
Tam so there was actually in a student
reader and it very early on and it's
downloadable from the website
somebody just poured that into
OmniGraffle I believe for the Mac
platform so people do it for just you
know designer I meant a drawing drawing
I should say ie there was an interesting
blog entry and experiment that I did
patterns are not components oh I agree
right but in our case we can cheat a
little bit because the composition model
of messaging is so simple which is
essentially I put a line between this
two box right that you can get pretty
far for let's say I would say at least
sort of educational purposes by making
components for each patterns and
chaining them together right it has its
certain limitations like I already said
about a channel yeah you might pick a
sort of point-to-point persistent yeah
chanting so you you can't really do
always those but you know I can put a
router and a splitter and an aggregator
and a transformer yeah I can chain those
together so what I did is I actually
build a little tool kit which it's you
know each thing is it's own individual
process that talk over em smq it's
already a pretty low tech and it's
downloadable from the website as well
and you can sort of build little
solutions out of your patterns there the
reasons of course that works or the
reason I could cheat if you wish is like
hey I fixed all assumptions so this
thing only runs in windows.net there's a
few XML messages right like I fixed all
the other the other parameters and I
picked exactly the kind of patterns that
lend themselves well to doing this and
there's a third main reason it works
because I resorted to other programming
languages to absorb the variability
points like for example my transformer
pattern component it takes an
accessibility transform yeah well my
splitter takes an XPath expression yeah
so since you have a whole programming
language right behind it I mean that's
the kind of like I thought I just move
the problem it's ago I have this one
common component it's like no it's
really just kind of like interpreter for
whole new language yeah so so you got to
be quite honest there
and I highlight that because there's so
many vendors going out there and say oh
this only requires configuration there's
no programming here yeah and then you
see these XPath expressions is a colon
colon ancestor simplistic language for
data transformation right so it is
programming yeah of course and it's
sometimes tough programming it's very
functional expressive it's hard to debug
and so that's why I highlight the fact I
was very honest that I cheated there and
say hey I just lay I moved the problem
from one language to another yeah but so
yes to some extent the messaging
patterns are unique and that you can
kind of make components out of them but
it's more I use it purely for
educational right so so people have done
this mostly for drawing towards which i
think is a very good use of it would be
an interesting experiment to actually
use monitoring development to generate
system configurations and mqa series
configurations for example from these
drawings which is from the generative
point-of-view no problem and that would
give you if you know in a beginner prize
would give you this like composer for
managing your messaging infrastructure
could be a nice experiment yes you can
definitely generate based on some
property intent is something that's not
very well translated into code so no you
have to specify these things in the
model you have to represent your intent
in some formal way mm-hmm what I think
what is quite useful we've done a lot of
visualizations so with the same toolkit
that I just mentioned where you put
these patterns together you can actually
draw you a messaging diagram because it
uses the control bus pattern which is
part of the systems management pattern
stuff the last ones I mentioned and
after the last last category actually
and so it knows who sends messages where
and it makes you a message flow graph
and for example what you could do there
you could annotate your individual
components say I really am an enricher
like my purpose is really to be a
message and richer and then you could
feed that into this automatic
diagramming tool and it could pick the
right icon right
haven't done that yet but there could be
a quite useful application where sort of
the pattern iconic language and the
extra system correspond correspond
correspond a bit more so that I mean
pretty much completes a category systems
management is the last one and it's all
the things that deal with stuff that is
not the main flow of traffic and
initially that sounds like wow
why would I not like you know why would
I want to do something else except get
my messages from A to B okay that's my
whole purpose of my messaging system is
to get data across but once you start to
realize and look at any other protocol
or system look at the telephone system
you know there's a lot of out-of-band
information in the telephone the best
story was always you know the Captain
Crunch story right where they used a
specific tone combination to indicate
the end of a call and there was
obviously out-of-band information but
iPhone she they used in Bane frequencies
to do that so so there was a little
whistle you could blow and then the
phone would stop collecting toll and so
that's like about the connection was
there yeah exactly because because it
wouldn't actually physically hang up it
just like basically so you could go to
the phone dial a number and blow the
little whistle and then you know the
thing the thing would go so that teaches
you a good lesson about separating out
of band and but any sophisticated
communication scheme I mean tcp/ip they
are there surrounding information
protocol etc there's a lot more packets
going over your network right just
application packet yeah yeah and
messaging the same thing you kind of
want to know what's going on so for
example a a control bus yeah we're we're
message where were applications besides
just having application related messages
they also send maybe statistics or
update messages or maybe they can get
controlled I have a little example in
the book where so you use a router to do
active failover so you don't want to do
competing consumers for example so
generally failover you can get very
easily by having multiple competing
consumers right if one of them goes away
you wouldn't pick any message anymore
the other guy does all the messages and
it gets a little bit slower but the the
beauty of that kind of architecture is
you still end up in the best situation
you cost possibly be in right right
because you know that's like one goes
away the best you can do is route them
all to the other and it's sort of
automatic yeah but there might be
situations where I don't want to do that
because let's say I have a cheap
provider and a premier provider so
normally I want to run on the cheap
provider now as I get volume discounts
and only that guy goes out do I want to
switch over yeah so that's where systems
management is really helpful it's you
can monitor flow of messages or you can
ping components notice that the one
actually got down right and I know the
one goes down and I
which the router over say messages now
go to the other one and I have a little
console with a little picture you know
like so this one goes red and the little
router actually redraws the router so
it's kind of cute you can play with the
icons where it's not someone like a mini
railroad yeah yeah you know the message
is now go here and they go there and
that's what a lot of system management
is about it's visualization control
knowing what's going on in the system
giving the administrators the relevant
information on all of it yeah or even
also putting administrative information
into the message like tracking where the
message has been can be quite useful
when something goes wrong for logging
because you don't want to keep too much
global state so a good place to keep
your stat is in the message right you
want to keep it in a special part so you
end up with the Captain Crunch problem
so you want to separate the application
payload from the header but then it
could be quite useful for example the
invalid message channel to know where
the message has been and have a history
so we call that message history
so the message carries its own history
and for example the other girl tip
corrective Enterprise actually had one
of those patterns built in I think it
wasn't used nearly enough because they
have these magic fields but it was
really hard to understand what he would
really use it for and that's of course
where the pattern comes in as well
that's what do you use it for yeah yeah
and that's about 65 patterns there's a
lot a lot in there yeah sure I only
mentioned even half of them by name yeah
no but but but I think this was actually
very useful and it was a bit long but I
think it doesn't matter so yeah so I
think this is there anything else you
want to say to our listeners leave them
with any pearls of wisdom before we wrap
up this episode you know one of the
questions we often get is sort of yeah
but you know in my specific case I can't
use messaging or messaging doesn't solve
problem X and and obviously the answer
there is of course messaging doesn't
solve all problems basically what we try
to do is give people sort of another
tool in their toolbox and suraíh and as
days there's a lot of cases where you
can use this it's probably more cases
than you would initially need right and
the good thing about
riding parents book as opposed to like
being a vendor the vendors always make a
believe that their product applies in
like virtually every in any scenario
versus for us you know it doesn't make a
difference yeah we can honestly tell you
is like hey here's where messaging
actually works for you and here's where
messaging doesn't and the patterns are
very honest so you're saying it doesn't
matter whether the people buy the book
read it and see that it solves their
problem or whether they buy the book
read it and it doesn't solve that
problem as long as they buy the book
yeah just make sure that just make sure
they they they buy the book but I mean
all joke aside a lot of the information
is on the website so there'll be all
patterns on the website you can download
the icons obviously not all the book
text is on the website so but it's not
you can definitely try before you buy so
we try to be I mean we believe patterns
are something very community oriented
absolutely yeah so that's why we like we
like to share okay thank you very much
for being on the show I think this was a
great episode yeah thank you yeah thank
you hope people have the time and
patience to actually listen to the ends
now we have good feedback also for long
long longer episodes and in worst case
we will make it to okay sounds good
thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details